AI, are we sick of talking about this
yet? Well, I hope not cuz you clicked on
this video about AI and it seems like
there is this whole public conversation
happening about the role of AI, whether
or not it's going to take people's jobs,
who's really benefiting from this new
technology, and if it's more hype than
help.
But, city planners also have to contend
with the physical side of this
cloud-based service.
AI requires data centers to work and the
resources being poured into these
facilities is kind of crazy. A
hyperscale data center designed for AI
can use as much power and water as a
mid-size city.
The thing is, this isn't exactly new
territory for a city planner. Planners
have had to deal with challenging land
uses since the beginning of the
profession. There's a group of places
called locally unwanted land uses or
LULUs that often have a challenging time
getting built because nobody wants to
live next to them. Classic examples
include landfills, feedlots, airports,
and sewage treatment plants. If you're a
NIMBY, housing is a LULU. A veteran city
planner will have likely gone through
the process for a LULU and have the
battle scars to prove it. These uses
often require extensive environmental
review, public outreach processes, and
lengthy permit review. But, while these
data centers may be just the next big
LULU, they are also something different.
Their resource use patterns are
different, their general usefulness is
different, and the level of investment
is different as well. Let's talk about
what happens when Big Tech and hundreds
of billions of dollars interacts with
local planning after the bike bell.
>> [bell]
>> So, AI data centers are the hot topic
right now in the planning world and for
good reason. Currently, the United
States has about 3,000 data centers in
operation, but according to Pew
Research, 1,500 new data centers are
planned or under construction. And these
new data centers are often quite a bit
larger than their predecessors. This is
a big deal because data centers come
with some pretty significant
environmental downsides. The biggest one
you may have heard of is water.
A typical data center, like the one of
the 3,000 in operation, uses about the
same amount of water as 1,000 homes. And
unlike other big water users like power
plants and agriculture, data centers use
municipal water. It's the same water
that the houses use. They don't pump it
out of the ground or take it directly
from a river. So, there's a potentially
large impact to a local government or
agency's ability to provide water to all
of its users when a data center moves
in. And the mega data centers like the
new ones they're building with for AI
could use the same amount of water as a
city of 50,000 residents. Power is
another massive challenge for local
governments and agencies around data
centers. It's probably the biggest
concern, honestly, because the demand
for most of these mega data centers is
being met by building new carbon dioxide
emitting power plants, typically natural
gas. Not a clean energy source, by the
way, despite the marketing hype. Or by
not decommissioning plants scheduled for
decommissioning. That means they pollute
longer than they would have otherwise.
The kind of sad thing here is that we're
right in the middle of a power
generation revolution where renewable
sources, primarily solar, are helping us
decarbonize rapidly. That's really,
really good news. Super exciting. But
these data centers are like unexpected
headwinds right as we have a safe port
in our sights.
Water and power tend to get all the
attention, but noise is a big issue for
those living near these things. It's
It's more of a localized issue as noise
tends to be intense but close by but
then falls off kind of quickly. But for
the people close, it's issue number one.
For more on this, check out the Business
Insider video on data centers. They
interview a resident living near one and
he talks about his experience with the
noise. That video was nominated for an
Emmy award, so the whole thing is
actually worth your time. Okay, so we
know what the environmental costs are
associated with building a data center.
Now, the question becomes, are the
benefits worth the cost?
Another way of thinking about it is
this. Are these new massive AI data
centers truly necessary? I think this
question is actually relevant because
it's the argument used to justify LULUs.
Nobody wants a coal-fired power plant in
their county, but everyone agrees that
providing electricity is necessary for
day-to-day life. Somebody has to live in
that same county as the power plant.
Now, obviously we have better ways of
generating power, but you get the idea.
Electricity is seen as a universal good
thing, and people are willing to put up
with some of the negative side effects.
The argument is the same for airports.
We all like to fly, but nobody wants to
live near the airport. Everyone wants
their trash picked up from their house,
but nobody wants to live near the
landfill.
NIMBYs want vibrant communities, but
don't want to live near other people.
So, let's go back to data centers. The
new mega data centers we're talking
about in this video are designed to
train AI models and then use them to
generate responses to prompts.
I know that a great many people find
LLMs and other AI uses to be helpful.
From what I understand, AI has made
coding quite a bit easier, for example.
But, many people are skeptical of the
benefits of AI. And many people, myself
included, don't really just need AI much
in their day-to-day life, or find it
annoying. Like, when I use Google, I get
an annoying wrong search summary.
I think everyone can agree that
electricity is universally a good thing
and everyone uses it, unless you're
fully off-grid, I guess. But, you can't
really say the same about AI.
Okay, so if these data centers are so
bad, why are communities actually
allowing them and or even courting them?
Two reasons. Well, it's really one
reason, but at two different places. The
reason is money, first at the local
level. Cities need tax revenues to pay
for services they provide. Things like
fire protection, paved roads, and parks.
An AI data center can help a city buy
new playgrounds, increase staff at the
senior center, and do other good things
community members want. Elected
officials like city council members want
to say that under their administration,
more seniors played bingo than ever
before, for example.
But, there are plenty of communities who
are rejecting these data centers
straight up and for all the downsides I
already mentioned. Many city councils
have passed moratoriums or halts on any
new data center projects in their
communities. Some cities have made it a
requirement that voters have to approve
any new data center projects in the
community as well.
And in June 2026, the city of Monterey
Park, California, passed a ballot
measure straight up banning any data
centers.
This was in response to an earlier
possible data center project. It's the
first time a city has banned them
outright through the ballot box.
And it passed with 86% of the vote. 86%.
That's all well and good, but the reason
they're still being built in some
communities is money.
Not just for local tax revenues, though
that's a factor, but because companies
are building data centers are actively
lobbying for statewide legislation
allowing them. It's called state
preemption.
It's basically like AI companies are in
a restaurant and they don't like the
service, so they call the manager. State
authority trumps local authority, and
that data center is getting a comped
dessert and and getting built.
The wonderful thing about city planning,
in my mind, is that it's sort of a great
equalizer. You can be a big corporation,
but you still have to put your office
campus plan through a planning
commission and city council meeting,
just like a small apartment building
developed by a local guy. Steve Jobs had
to present his proposal for the new
Apple campus to the Cupertino City
Council. It's an example of the beauty
of local democracy. The world's most
valuable company had to ask permission
to build a campus from local elected
officials. So, you might be thinking
that local governments can regulate and
decide on whether or not they want a
data center in their community. And in
some places, that's true, but actually
not all places. That's because of
statewide legislation that fast-tracks
AI data center construction.
How can states do this? Well, legally
speaking, city governments only have the
rights that the states give them. Home
rule, or the idea cities get to govern
themselves, is sort of a privilege that
states give to cities. It's not actually
a right, and states can preempt that
whenever they want. Your view on whether
or not this is a good thing probably
depends on how you feel about certain
urban planning issues.
California is preempting home rule to
require cities to plan for more housing.
If you are a YIMBY, yes in my backyard,
you think that's a good thing. Other
more conservative states use it to
subvert the plans of more liberal
cities.
For example, some conservative-leaning
states prohibit local governments from
setting their own higher minimum wages.
Preemption is also what's happening in
the data center space. West Virginia, of
all places, might be the boldest state.
Their 2025 power generation and
consumption act creates specific
policies at the state level for
high-impact data center districts.
Data centers built in these districts
are exempt from all local zoning, noise
ordinances, and building regulations.
Basically, if a data center developer
wants to build one in West Virginia,
they can just get approval from the
state and do whatever they want. Crazily
enough, the first draft of that bill
directed all tax revenues to the state
government, giving none to local
governments.
The final draft allocated to 30% to the
county the data center's located in, and
5% to be split among the other counties
in the state. 65% of all those tax
revenues, though, will still go to the
state government. With this kind of law,
a data center project can seemingly pop
up out of nowhere, as nobody at the
local level even needs to be notified.
The most prominent example of this
happening was near the cities of Thomas
and Davis in rural West Virginia. A
resident was flipping through her
newspaper and found an obscure legal
notice disclosing potential air
pollution impacts for a proposed
facility in her area. She sent the
notice around town, and nobody knew what
it was. They eventually found out it was
for a data center, and an entirely new
natural gas plant to power the servers.
By the time they had found out about it,
there wasn't much they could do. The
state had already given out their
approvals, and many of the documents
they could find were heavily redacted,
making it difficult for residents to
know what they were up against.
Fundamental data that people developing
this data center said that at full
build-out, the data center could span
10,000 acres and be one of the largest
data center campuses in the world. All
of this is without any local planning
involved at all.
Residents have not given up their
efforts to stop the project, but it's an
uphill battle given the regulatory
environment. It's just all pitched
against them. West Virginia's laws may
be the most data center-friendly, but
other states are following suit. In
Louisiana, the state subverted local
control by pre-zoning a massive campus
area for Meta's Hyperion data center.
They also gave the project massive tax
breaks.
Nearby residents had little recourse as
the state was already directly working
with Meta. This data center will use up
more power than the entire rest of the
state of Louisiana and require the
construction of three new gas power
plants to meet the energy needs.
Pennsylvania has passed a law creating a
state board that pre-designates sites
for large-scale data centers and they
fast-track data center projects in those
areas. They've already identified 15
sites, mostly at retired power plant
locations.
Other states are pushing data centers
through by using their legal authorities
to manage utilities and regulate air
pollution.
Texas is a great example of this as most
counties in the state don't even have
the local authority to do zoning.
It's easy for the Electric Reliability
Council of Texas and the Public Utility
Commission to govern the production of
data centers with minimal public input
from local governments.
As kind of an aside, all of this data
center stuff reminds me of another tech
land use overlap, another Lulu,
warehouses. Most typified by the Amazon
warehouses allowing next-day and two-day
deliveries. They are large, hire a
relatively low number of workers, and
have disproportionate impacts on nearby
communities. The trucks create
significant air pollution in the nearby
area. The number of crashes in the
vicinity increase. And studies have
shown that these warehouses are often
located in low-income and minority
locations, creating environmental
justice concerns. Many communities
sought these warehouses out hoping for
property tax revenues. But again,
studies have shown that these property
taxes are low per acre and have not
offset the costs local governments bear
by having these warehouses in their
borders.
As a result, there have been a number of
communities that have passed moratoriums
on their construction. Sounds familiar,
right?
Like I said, data centers may be the
biggest, most difficult Lulu of recent
times, but it's not the first. Planners
really have seen it all. So, what can be
done to ensure data centers don't
disproportionately impact the local
communities? I know that some of you out
there would just like some kind of
national ban on data centers, but I hate
to tell you the political environment's
heading the opposite direction on that
one.
And don't think it's realistic,
particularly when some data centers
provide useful non-AI services that we
all do rely on. But, we can regulate
them. Regulation breeds innovation. If
cities and states say the data centers
need to limit their water and power use
to certain thresholds, you'd better
believe those tech companies would be
using their billions to meet those
thresholds. The problem is that many of
our elected officials seem to fall into
three groups. First, there are people
who have no idea about technology at all
and just vote cluelessly, seemingly.
Second, there are people who wrongly
believe that the internet and tech is a
wild west and cannot be regulated.
Regulation is impossible, and if it did
work, you'd be stifling innovation. And
the third kind of people are people who
receive large donations to do whatever
tech companies want.
This is why regulation will not occur
without significant public support for
them. Votes still matter. We need to be
supporting candidates that campaign on
AI data center regulation. We need to be
asking questions of these candidates.
These regulations could include
guarantees that utility rates will not
increase for residential customers as a
result of the construction of a new data
center, requirements that data centers
build their own power sources using
renewable power, public disclosures of
water use, and buffer zones around data
centers to reduce the impact of noise on
local communities.
Regulations could also ensure that data
center impact fees and property taxes go
to the communities they are located in
and not the state government. Data
centers are obviously a major current
event, and we just finished another one,
the World Cup. While I was definitely
cheering for my preferred team, the USA,
and then later Norway, I was also
thinking of the logistics of these major
sporting events. I was in LA during the
World Cup, though not the games, sadly.
I definitely wondered about mobility and
traffic. TomTom wondered too, and during
the tournament they created a traffic
index dashboard that helped visualize
traffic patterns around the 16 host
venues. It showed where congestion built
up, how quickly it peaked, and how it
spread across the surrounding road
network.
These traffic dynamics are not unique to
the event. They're recurring patterns
seen at major sporting events around the
world. Though the tournament is over,
the traffic index dashboard still works
and you can go check it out. I put a
link in the description.
At the time I'm filming this, the New
England Revolution of MLS hosted a game
yesterday in Gillette Stadium. They beat
Atlanta United 4-1 by the way.
You can see here that there's a traffic
peak at 6:00 p.m. before the 7:30
kickoff and another peak at 10:00 p.m.
after the game is over.
But there's more than just one graph.
And congestion is just one piece of the
puzzle. To actually plan for events like
this, you need to understand what's
driving those patterns and how different
parts of the network behave together.
And that's where a platform like
TomTom's Move Portal comes into play.
Move brings together different types of
traffic intelligence in one place.
Historic traffic stats understand
baseline behavior, origin-destination
analysis to see how people travel
between airports, hotels, and venues,
route monitoring to track key travel
corridors over time, junction analytics
to pinpoint pressure at intersections
around stadiums, and area analytics to
uncover any traffic insights in specific
areas such as access roads around a
stadium.
Altogether, you get a much clearer
picture of not just where things will
slow down, but where the network can
handle spikes in demand and where even
greater opportunities lie.
From proactively adjusting traffic flows
to implementing measures like re-timed
signals and transit priority. So, if you
want to see how traffic behaves around
stadiums during major sporting events,
check out TomTom's Football World
Championship Dashboard. And if you want
to understand what's really possible
with traffic intelligence, explore
TomTom's Move Portal. Go to
tomtom.com/citybeautiful
to explore the data for yourself and
check out the TomTom Move Portal free
for 30 days.